8.程序崩溃的时候你是怎么排查问题的
How do you troubleshoot issues when a program crashes

在程序里加一些代码，崩溃的时候就能产生dump文件，Windows底下可以使用windbg或者vs查看崩溃地方，Linux底下可以用vscode查看崩溃地方，或者直接使用gdb运行程序，崩溃时使用bt命令查看堆栈信息，还有一种方式，崩溃前会进入到一个系统回调函数中，定义那个回调函数，可以在那里把堆栈信息写到文件中，包括崩溃前的系统信息都可以获取到，Windows底下是和dump相关的一个回调函数，Linux底下是注册signal信号

Adding some code in the program allows generating a dump file when it crashes. Under Windows, you can use Windbg or Visual Studio to examine the crash location. In Linux, you can use VSCode to view the crash location or run the program directly using GDB. When a crash occurs, you can use the bt command in GDB to view the stack trace. Another approach（əˈprəʊtʃ 方法） involves entering a system callback function before the crash. By defining that callback function, you can write stack information to a file, including pre-crash system information. In Windows, this is associated（əˈsoʊsieɪtɪd 有关的） with a callback function related to dumps, while in Linux, it involves registering a signal handler

9.内存占满或者CPU占满的时候怎么找问题
How to troubleshoot when the memory is fully utilized（ˈjuːtəlaɪzd 被利用的） or the CPU is at full capacity

可以使用一些第三方工具，内存分析工具Valgrind和性能分析工具GNU Profiler找出大量消耗资源的代码段，或者在代码中添加日志，或者调试运行，然后中断，看堆栈信息判断问题出现的大致位置

You can use third-party tools such as memory analysis tool Valgrind and performance profiling tool GNU Profiler to identify resource-intensive code segments. Alternatively, you can add logs in the code, or debug the code by running it and interrupting（ɪntəˈrʌptɪŋ 中断） the process to examine stack traces, allowing you to roughly determine the location where the issue arises

10.说一下智能指针的用法
Discuss the usage of smart pointers

shared_ptr内部有一个引用计数，在拷贝时，引用计数会加1，释放时计数减1，如果为0就会释放内部申请的内存，unique_ptr是独占的，不能拷贝，性能比shared_ptr会好一些，weak_ptr是解决两个类互相包含对方shared_ptr，在释放时出现内存泄漏问题的，weak_ptr不能直接使用，要转成shared_ptr使用，weak_ptr在释放时引用计数不会变化

The shared_ptr maintains an internal reference count. When copied, the reference count is incremented, and when released, it is decremented. If the count becomes zero, the internally allocated memory is deallocated. unique_ptr represents（ˌreprɪˈzents 代表） exclusive ownership and cannot be copied, offering better performance compared to shared_ptr. weak_ptr is used to address issues of circular references between two classes holding each other via shared_ptr. It cannot be used directly and needs to be converted to shared_ptr before usage. Importantly, the reference count of weak_ptr does not change when it is released

11.说一下引用和指针的区别
Discuss the difference between references and pointers

引用时为变量起别名，指针是占用运行内存的，指针可能为空指针，引用不会
A reference is an alias（eɪliəs 别名） for a variable, while a pointer occupies runtime memory and may be a null pointer. References cannot be null

12.说一下右值引用和左值引用的区别
Discuss the difference between rvalue references and lvalue references

左值引用就是可以直接当成变量使用的引用，有值引用是存放右值的，右值例如常量，返回值，右值引用增加右值的生命周期，在过了右值定义之后，右值引用变为左值引用，可以当成变量使用

A left-value reference is a reference that can be used directly as a variable, while a right-value reference is used to store right-values, such as constants or return values. A right-value reference can extend the lifetime of a right-value. After the definition of the right-value, the right-value reference becomes a left-value reference and can be used like a variable

13.模板偏特化是怎么实现的
How is template specialization implemented

首先需要一个通用模板，然后实现偏特化模板，偏特化主要用于处理一些特殊情况，当其中一个参数为特定类型的时候，去掉通用模板中的typename，同时定义偏特化类或函数

First, you need a generic template. Then, implement a partial specialization of the template. Partial specialization is mainly used to handle specific cases. When one of the template parameters has a specific type, you remove the typename from the generic template and define the specialized class or function accordingly（əˈkɔːdɪŋli 相应的）

14.析构函数为什么是虚函数
Why is the destructor a virtual function

当子类继承父类的时候，如果定义的子类放到了父类指针中，当删除指针时，如果析构函数不为虚函数，则会出现内存泄漏

When a subclass inherits（ɪnˈherɪt 继承） from a parent class and an instance of the subclass is placed in a pointer of the parent class, if the destructor is not a virtual function, deleting the pointer may lead to memory leaks

15.构造函数可以是虚函数吗
Can a constructor be a virtual function

构造函数不可以是虚函数，构造函数在构造时还没有虚函数表，所以无法定义为虚函数

Constructors cannot be virtual functions. During construction, there is no virtual function table (vtable) yet, so it cannot be defined as a virtual function

16.说一下static的用法
Describe the usage of static

static可以用于定义静态变量，可以用于定义静态函数，也可以在类中定义静态函数，或静态变量，静态变量的生命周期是全局的，但是作用域只有在定义之后才可以使用，类中的静态函数可以直接调用，CPP中的全局静态函数只能在当前CPP中使用

static can be used to define static variables, static functions, and it can also be used in classes to define static member functions or static member variables. The lifetime of static variables is global, but their scope（范围） is limited to the file or function where they are defined. Static functions within a class can be called without creating an instance of the class. Global static functions in a CPP file are only visible within that file

17.C++11里你用过哪些新特性
What new features have you used in C++11

用过thread，mutex，atomic，condition_variable
have used features like thread, mutex, atomic, and condition_variable in C++11

18.说一下原子操作的原理
Explain the principle of atomic operations

分为硬件级和软件级，硬件级由芯片中的系统函数保证原子操作，软件级由汇编或加锁完成原子操作

It is divided into hardware level and software level. At the hardware level, atomic operations are ensured by system functions within the chip, while at the software level, atomic operations are achieved through assembly language or locking mechanisms

19.说一下锁的用法
Explain the usage of locks

多线程访问同一块内存的时候，需要同时上锁，保证同一时间只有一条线程访问内存块，以免发生数据冲突

When multiple threads access（ˈækses 访问） the same block of memory, it is necessary to lock it simultaneously（sɪm(ə)lˈteɪniəsli 同时的） to ensure that only one thread accesses the memory block at any given time. This helps prevent data conflicts

20.多线程如何使用
How to use multithreading

首先创建线程池类，在类中创建线程并将线程指针放入vector，执行的线程中增加信号量开始等待任务，然后封装一个task类，在task类中定义一个虚函数，在子类中实现具体执行内容，然后将task送到线程池类中的任务队列，再发送信号量，线程从任务队列中取出任务，执行虚函数中的具体业务逻辑

First, create a thread pool class. Within the class, create threads and store their pointers in a vector. In the threads' execution, add a semaphore（seməfɔː(r)） to start waiting for tasks. Then, define a task class. Within the task class, define a virtual function, and implement the specific execution content in its subclasses. Send the task to the task queue（kju 队列） in the thread pool class and signal the semaphore. Threads then retrieve tasks from the queue and execute the specific business logic in the virtual function

21.多进程怎样通信
How to communicate between multiple processes

首先申请多个共享内存，形成共享内存池，再申请一块共享内存用于存放接收方进程ID，以8个字节为一单元，前4个字节存放接收方进程ID，后4个字节用于表示现在是否写入完成，共享内存的索引值对于具体的共享内存块，在发送数据时在存放序号的共享内存中写入对方进程ID，在写完后将后4个字节从0改为1，并通过信号量通知对方进程，对方进程收到信号后从共享内存中取出数据，并将1改为0

First, allocate multiple shared memory blocks to form a shared memory pool. Then, allocate another shared memory block to store the ID of the receiving process. Divide this block into units of 8 bytes each, where the first 4 bytes store the ID of the receiving process, and the latter 4 bytes indicate whether the writing is completed (0 for not completed, 1 for completed). The index value in shared memory corresponds to a specific shared memory block.
During data transmission, when sending data, write the ID of the receiving process to the shared memory block storing the sequence（sikerense 序号） number. After writing, change the last 4 bytes from 0 to 1, and notify the receiving process through a semaphore. When receiving the signal, the receiving process retrieves the data from the shared memory and changes 1 to 0

22.当需要你写一个公共基础库的时候需要怎样写测试用例
When you need to write a common foundational library, how do you go about writing test cases

首先将函数的参数以及返回值写上注释，每个功能都对应一个示例，并配上对应的预期结果，当用户使用时可以参考示例写代码，如果有流程性的功能，会配上具体的测试函数，以及输出函数

First, document the function's parameters and return values with comments. Each functionality should have corresponding examples, along with the expected results. Users can refer to these examples when writing code. If there are functions with procedural(prəˈsiːdʒərəl 流程上的) aspects(ˈæspekts 方面), specific test functions and output functions will be provided

23.说一下map和unorderedmap的区别
Explain the difference between map and unordered_map

map底层用的是红黑树，unorderedmap用的是hash桶，hash桶是先创建16个桶，随机存放，当负载超过0.75后，扩容，重新分配数据，这样无论数据量多少，增删的时间复杂度都为常量

map uses a red-black tree as its underlying data structure, while unordered_map uses a hash table. In the hash table, 16 buckets are initially created, and elements are randomly placed into these buckets. When the load factor exceeds 0.75, the hash table is resized, and data is rehashed and redistributed. This ensures constant time complexity for insertions and deletions, regardless of the amount of data

24.说一下vector的扩容机制
Explain the resizing mechanism of a vector

当超过上限时，重新申请一块内存，大小为原来的1.5倍，并将原数据拷贝至新内存
When the capacity（kəˈpæsəti 容量） limit is exceeded（ɪkˈsi:dɪd 溢出的）, a new block of memory is allocated, sized at 1.5 times the original, and the existing data is copied to the new memory

25.说一下vector和list的区别
Explain the differences between vector and list

vector是连续的内存，list是链表，vector访问效率更高，list增删效率高
vector uses contiguous（kənˈtɪɡjuəs 连续的） memory, while list is a linked list. vector provides higher access efficiency, whereas list excels in insertion and deletion efficiency

28.new和malloc的区别
Differences between 'new' and 'malloc

new是在malloc的基础上增加执行了构造函数，如果含有虚函数则会多创建一个虚函数表
new is an extension of malloc that additionally calls the constructor. If the object has virtual functions, new will also create a virtual function table

29.说一下lambda表达式的用法
Explain the usage of lambda expressions

表达式是一个无名函数，分为值传递和引用传递，值传递是将数值拷贝进去，引用传递是通过引用的方式传进去，在函数内部可以更改变量值

The expression is an anonymous（əˈnɒnɪməs 匿名） function, divided into pass by value and pass by reference. Pass by value involves copying the numerical value into it, while pass by reference means passing by reference, allowing the modification of variable values inside the function

30.内联函数怎么使用
How to use inline functions

在函数前增加inline关键字，函数体不能过长，内联函数在编译时会将函数去掉，直接将函数体内容编译进代码，效率更高，但生成的可执行文件大小会更大

To use inline functions, add the inline keyword before the function declaration. The function body should not be too long. During compilation, the compiler removes the function and directly includes its body in the code. This approach improves efficiency（ɪˈfɪʃnsi 效率）, but it may result in a larger size for the generated executable file

31.externC的用法是什么
What is the usage of extern C

在代码对接时，以C语言的方式编译代码，会去掉函数前缀和后缀
When integrating code, compiling it in C language style removes function prefixes and suffixes

32.栈和堆的区别
Differences between the stack and the heap

栈空间可以自动回收内存，堆空间不会，栈的访问速度更快，但是容量小，一般为几兆大小
The stack space can automatically reclaim（rɪˈkleɪm 回收） memory, while the heap space does not. The stack has faster access speed but smaller capacity, typically（tɪpɪkli 通常） a few megabytes

33.怎样在已申请的内存上创建对象
How to create objects on allocated memory

object* p2 = new(p1)object;

34.返回值可以用于重载吗
Can the return value be used for overloading

返回值不可以用于重载，重载只能重载参数不同的函数
The return value cannot be used for overloading; overloading can only be done with functions that have different parameters

35.说一下封装继承多态的特性
Explain the features of encapsulation, inheritance, and polymorphism

封装是将函数和变量封装到一个类中，便于使用，面对对象编程，继承是将类的函数以及变量全部复制给子类，供子类使用减少代码，多态是虚函数实现，子类继承父类虚函数，在调用时，使用子类虚函数以实现不同的功能

Encapsulation（ɪnˌkæpsjuˈleɪʃ(ə)n 封装） involves bundling functions and variables into a class for ease of use in object-oriented programming. Inheritance（ɪnˈherɪtəns 继承） is the process of copying all functions and variables from a class to a subclass, reducing code in file. Polymorphism（pɒlɪˈmɔːfɪz(ə)m 多态） is implemented through virtual functions; when a subclass inherits a virtual function from a parent class, it can achieves different function

36.虚继承的作用
The purpose of virtual inheritance

当多个子类继承父类后，多个子类就同时含有相同的函数，当定义一个新的类同时继承了这些子类后，就需要使用虚继承，避免这些相同的函数发生冲突

When multiple subclasses inherit from a common parent class, they all simultaneously contain the same functions. When defining a new class that inherits from these subclasses, the use of virtual inheritance is necessary to avoid conflicts arising from these duplicated function

37.模板中class和template的区别
Difference between 'class' and 'template' in templates

当使用模板定义的函数时，必须使用typename，其他时候可以和class互换使用
When using a function defined with templates, 'typename' must be used; otherwise, it can be exchanged with 'class' in other situations

38.stdcall和cdecl的区别
Difference between stdcall and cdecl

stdcall从左向右入参，多用于Windows，cdecl从右向左入参，是标准函数调用方式

Stdcall passes parameters from left to right, commonly used in Windows; cdecl passes parameters from right to left and is the standard calling convention

39.内存泄漏怎么排查
How to troubleshoot memory leaks

我写过一个内存泄漏排查工具，重载new和delete，当申请内存时会进入到重载的new函数中，在函数中记录指针值和堆栈信息，以及代码行数，存入map，指针值为key，在delete的时候把对应的指针删掉，程序结束时map中残留的指针就是内存泄漏的地方

I have developed a memory leak detection tool by overloading new and delete. When memory is allocated, it enters the overloaded new function, where the pointer value, stack information, and code line number are recorded and stored in a map, with the pointer value as the key. When deleting, the corresponding pointer is removed. At the end of the program, the remaining pointers in the map indicate the locations of memory leaks

40.C++中异常时怎么使用的
How are exceptions used in C++

用try和catch捕获异常，进入到异常时跳跃式执行的，可以在异常函数中执行错误处理代码

Use try and catch to catch exceptions; it executes in a jump-like manner when an exception occurs. Error-handling code can be executed in the exception function

41.struct和class的区别
Difference between 'struct' and 'class'

struct中的函数和变量默认是公有的，class中默认的函数和变量是私有的
Functions and variables in a struct are public by default, while in a class, the default visibility for functions and variables is private

42.说一下类中有哪些默认函数
List some of the default functions in a class

构造函数，析构函数，拷贝构造函数，拷贝赋值函数，移动构造函数，移动赋值函数
Constructor, destructor, copy constructor, copy assignment operator, move constructor, move assignment operator

43.explicit的作用
Purpose of 'explicit'

用于修饰构造函数，表示这个类在生成时只能使用括号的形式，不能使用等号，防止混淆
Used to modify constructors, indicating that the class can only be instantiated using parentheses and not with the equal sign, to prevent confusion

44.友元函数的作用
Purpose of friend functions

在类内声明友元后，对方就可以使用该类的私有函数和私有成员变量
After declaring a friend inside a class, the friend can access the private functions and private member variables of that class

45.说一下静态库和动态库的区别和优缺点
Explain the differences and advantages/disadvantages between static libraries and dynamic libraries

静态库在编译时会将代码编译进可执行文件，只会编译需要的函数，可执行文件体积更小，执行速度更快，动态库可以动态加载和卸载，方便在主程序不关闭的情况下替换动态库，动态库在加载时即便只使用一个函数也会加载一整个动态库，开销比较大，当多个文件加载同一个动态库时，Linux下是同一块内存空间，而Windows下是两块内存空间

Static libraries compile code into the executable at compile time, including only the necessary functions, resulting in a smaller executable size and faster execution speed. Dynamic libraries can be dynamically loaded and unloaded, allowing easy replacement without closing the main program. Dynamic libraries, however, load the entire library even if only one function is used, incurring larger overhead. When multiple files load the same dynamic library, on Linux, they share the same memory space, while on Windows, they use separate（seprət 分开的） memory spaces