排查 troubleshoot
问题 issues
崩溃 crashes
程序 program
项目 project
堆栈信息 Stack information
获取信息 Get information
占满 full
分析 analysis
性能 Performance
提升 Improve
消耗 consume
迭代器 iterator ɪtəˈreɪtə
中断 interrupt ɪntəˈrʌpt
判断 determine
引用计数 reference count
申请内存 allocated memory
独占内存 exclusive （eksklusive） memory
解决问题 solve the problem
引用和指针 references and pointers
别名 alias（eɪliəs）
变量 variable
空指针 a null pointer
运行内存 runtime memory
生命周期  lifetime
延长 extend 
偏特化 specialization 
实现 implement ˈɪmplɪment
实例  instance
通用的 generic dʒəˈnerɪk
封装继承多态 Encapsulation ɪnˌkæpsjuˈleɪʃ(ə)n, Inheritance ɪnˈherɪtəns, Polymorphism pɒlɪˈmɔːfɪz(ə)m
虚函数表  virtual function table
条件变量 condition_variable
硬件级和软件级 hardware level and software level
芯片 Chip tʃɪp
汇编 Assembly
功能 Functionality
访问 access ˈækses
发生 occurs əˈkɜːz
冲突 conflicts
存储 restore
子类 subclass
业务逻辑 Business logic
取出 retrieve rɪˈtriːv
单元 units
完成 complete
参数 parameters
文档 document
注释 comment
相关的 corresponding
预期结果 expected results
参考 refer 
示例 examples 
输出 output 
红黑树  red-black tree
hash桶 hash buckets
负载 load 
溢出 exceeds ɪkˈsiːd
扩容 resize
重新分配 redistributed ˌriːdɪˈstrɪbjuːtɪd
无论 Regardless of
数量 amount
时间复杂度 Time complexity
保证 ensures 
常量 constant 
上限 limit 
大小 size
倍数 times
连续的 contiguous kənˈtɪɡjuəs
链表 linked list
效率 efficiency ɪˈfɪʃ(ə)nsi
匿名 anonymous əˈnɒnɪməs
值传递引用传递 pass by value pass by reference
通常情况 usual juːʒuəl circumstances sɜːkəmstənsɪz
编译 compiler 
可执行文件  executable file
去掉 remove
前缀和后缀 prefixes and suffixes
堆和栈 heap and stack space
回收 reclaim rɪˈkleɪm
几兆 a few megabytes
重载 overloading
方便的 convenient
作用 purpose
入参 passes parameters
标准 standard 
调用约定 calling convention
残留 remain
异常 exception
跳跃  jump
构造函数，析构函数，拷贝构造函数，拷贝赋值函数，移动构造函数，移动赋值函数
Constructor, destructor, copy constructor, copy assignment operator, move constructor, move assignment operator
括号 parentheses pəˈrenθəsiːz
双冒号 Double Colon
静态库 Static libraries
动态库 Dynamic libraries
优点 Advantages ədˈvæntɪdʒ
缺点 Disadvantages
卸载 unload
主程序 main program
即使 even if
提升 improve
信号 semaphore（seməfɔː(r)）
实现 achieves
分开的 separate
浏览器 browser
网线 network cable
离职 resign
NVIDIA is a globally renowned（rɪˈnaʊnd） company, and I am eager（ˈiːɡə(r） to become a part of your team and work together
我非常信任英伟达，所以我没有什么问题，只是我想问下，这个面试结果大概多久能出来
I have a lot of trust in NVIDIA, so I don't have any question. I just wanted to ask, how long does it typically take for the interview results to be available
我现在已经有offer了，但是我非常想加入英伟达，所以来英伟达面试
I currently have an offer, but I am very interested in joining NVIDIA, so I came for an interview with NVIDIA